## Neil Ranada

### User Experience Research & Design

Designer and veteran U.S. Navy pilot with over 10 years of professional experience in aviation, aerospace, and defense. I practice design thinking backed by quantitative and qualitative research. I solve challenging problems by making mobile apps, websites, and other digital products easier to use so that people can focus on what matters most to them.

# Experience

#### Freelance User Experience (UX) Researcher & Designer

Jan 2016 to Present

- Conduct iterative research, design, and testing to increase user control over map features in a mobile app
- Refine wireframes & mockups to streamline customer checkout process for a medical research fundraiser website
- Design content management prototype for usability testing to prove app features are recognizable and intuitive to use

#### **Mission Planning Analyst**

Apr 2014 to Dec 2015

- Mission Planning Analyst for the director of all U.S. Navy strategic assets in the Middle East
- Utilized specialized planning skills to advise leadership on options for allocating strategic assets each valued at \$1.5M+
- Conducted quality control for a successful \$3.4M test flight project for Raytheon
- Facilitated over 40 training events resulting in successful evaluation and certification

#### **Aviation Safety Program Manager**

May 2011 to Apr 2014

- Safety Program Manager for the director of all U.S. Navy helicopter assets throughout the Western U.S. and Pacific
- Oversaw safety programs for 13 aviation organizations consisting of 139 aircraft and over 3,600 personnel
- Advised executives on safety matters including hazards, mishaps, and system safety
- · Analyzed investigation reports and recommended corrective actions to address material and human causal factors
- · Reviewed and prioritized customer complaints, and collaborated with cross-functional teams to find timely solutions

#### **Squadron Helicopter Pilot**

Apr 2008 to Apr 2011

- Aircraft carrier based Helicopter Pilot leading crews in \$20M aircraft in search & rescue and disaster relief missions
- Led a small team solving complex logistics problems in a fast-paced, dynamic, multi-national environment
- Directed daily schedule to ensure completion of training and real-world flight operations

## Education

M.A. International Relations – University of Oklahoma – Norman, OK

B.A. Geography – University of Washington – Seattle, WA

Arthur UX Workshops – Mapping Micro-Experiences, Digital Prototyping, Testing Designs with Users – San Diego, CA

Digital Telepathy Workshops – Essentials of Product Design, Essentials of Customer Interviews – San Diego, CA

Bloc, io – User Experience Design, User Interface Design, Front-end Development – Remote

# Design Processes & Tools

Personas, User Stories & Flows, Wireframes, Mockups, Usability Testing, Prototype, Sketch App, InVision, Adobe XD